Peace Collection, 1825-1984
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Peace collection
1825-1984
MS 437
28 boxes; 7 volumes (13.25 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Peace activists. The Peace Collection is comprised largely of published materials documenting the work of women's peace activism from the early nineteenth century to the 1980s. The bulk of the collection dates from 1925 to 1977 and focuses on U.S. and international peace organizations, and individual women leaders in peace movements. Types of material include organizational records, newspaper clippings, articles, periodicals, pamphlets, flyers, biographical articles, writings, correspondence, newsletters, conference materials, minutes, reports, manuals, books, photographs, and videotapes. A substantial portion of the collection documents the activities of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF) and individual members, circa 1919-1977. Other organizations represented include the National Congress of Women, Women's Christian Temperance Union, Another Mother for Peace, National Committee for the Cause and Cure of War, Order of the Unicorn, Women's Peace Party, World Gathering of Women for Disarmament, American League Against War and Fascism, American Peace Society, and the World Movement for World Federal Government. There are small amounts of material on individual peace activists such as Jane Addams, Emily Greene Balch, Marie Curie, Lucia Ames Mead, and Maude Miner Hadden (Smith class 1901), among others. Photographs, printed material and a videotape document the "Women's Pentagon Action," November 1980. The collection also includes published works on women and peace.
The Peace Collection is comprised largely of published materials documenting the work of women's peace activism from the early nineteenth century to the 1980s. The bulk of the collection dates from 1925 to 1977 and focuses on U.S. and international peace organizations, and individual women leaders in peace movements. Types of material include organizational records, newspaper clippings, articles, periodicals, pamphlets, flyers, biographical articles, writings, correspondence, newsletters, conference materials, minutes, reports, manuals, books, photographs, and videotapes. A substantial portion of the collection documents the activities of the Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (WILPF) and individual members, circa 1919-1977. Other organizations represented include the National Congress of Women, Women's Christian Temperance Union, Another Mother for Peace, National Committee for the Cause and Cure of War, Order of the Unicorn, Women's Peace Party, World Gathering of Women for Disarmament, American League Against War and Fascism, American Peace Society, and the World Movement for World Federal Government. There are small amounts of material on individual peace activists such as Jane Addams, Emily Greene Balch, Marie Curie, Lucia Ames Mead, and Maude Miner Hadden (Smith class 1901), among others. Photographs, printed material and a videotape document the "Women's Pentagon Action," November 1980. The collection also includes published works on women and peace.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. GENERAL
II. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
III. ORGANIZATIONS
OVERSIZED MATERIALS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, but researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form, agreeing to not identify participants in Women's Pentagon Action records.
Information on Use
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. Included are duplicates of material from the Swarthmore Peace Collection. Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
Search Terms
Addams, Jane, 1860-1935; National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War (U.S.); Women's International League for Peace and Freedom--History--Sources; Pacifism--History; Pacifists--United States--Biography--Sources; Peace movements--History--Sources; Peace--Societies, etc.--History--Sources; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975--Protest movements--Sources Women and peace--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women's Pentagon Action (November 1980); World War, 1914-1918--Protest movements; World War, 1939-1945--Protest movements
Contents List
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - Clippings and articles, 1920-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "All Pink Sisters: The War Department and the Feminist Movement," paper by Joan Jenson, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anti-pacifist, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Owlet, December 6-20, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Peace flag, 1897-98 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets, 1835, 1888-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Peacemaker, January and March, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Propaganda," 1939, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - World government, 1932-48, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conference of Women for International Cooperation Year, 1960, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women, Earth, Feminist Peace Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women's peace activities against the Vietnam War
    - Articles and pamphlets, 1972-73, undated (Box 1A, Folder 1)
    - Flyers, notices, posters and writings, 1967-71, undated (Box 1A, Folder 2)
    - Canada Conference, April 9-12, 1971 (Box 1A, Folder 3)
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Collected biographies and bibliographies (incl. Women Peace-makers, by H. Spaull, and "Women and Peace"), 1924-83 (Box 1A, Folder 4)
  - Balch, Emily Greene, 1917-65, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hughan, Jessie, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mead, Lucia Ames, 1905-35, undated (Box 2, Folder 3-6)
  - Peace Pilgrim (3 video tapes), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Roelofs, Henrietta, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sutro, Florentine Scholle, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Suttner, Bertha von (Tuttle, Florence Guertin), 1918, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Wentworth, Lydia G., 1924, 1945, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Wynner, Edith, 1944-46, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Caldicott, Helen, 1978-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS
  - American League Against War and Fascism, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Peace Society (Boston), undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Another Mother for Peace, [see box 4] (Box 3)
  - Appeal of Women to the World's Statesmen, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Citizens for Participation in Political Action, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Coalition for a Non-Nuclear World, 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 4a)
  - Committee for World Development and World Disarmament, 1954, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Crusade for World Government, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Disarmament Committee of the Women's International Organizations, 1921-40, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Entente Mondiale Pour la Paix, 1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation, 1938, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Fund for Peace, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Greenham Common Women's Peace Camp, 1984, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10a)
  - International Committee of Women for Permanent Peace, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - League for Permanent Peace, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - League of Nations, 1920-38, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War, [see box 5 and books on shelf] (Box 3)
  - National Council for Reduction of Armaments, 1922, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Council for the Prevention of War, 1928-70, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Order of the Unicorn, 1963-69, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Peace through Knowledge, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Voice of Women: New England: Peace Boutique, 1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Women Strike for Peace, [see box 6] (Box 3)
  - Women's Action Committee for Lasting Peace, 1944-50, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Women's Committee to Oppose Conscription, [see box 7] (Box 3)
  - Women's Encampment for a Future of Peace and Justice, [see box 7] (Box 3)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, [see boxes 8-24] (Box 3)
  - Women's Party for Survival, 1981, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - W.C.T.U.: Peace Department, 1916-17, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Women's Peace Crusade, 1919-30, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Women's Peace Party, 1915-19, undated, [see books on shelf] (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Women's Peace Union of the Western Hemisphere, 1920-21, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Women's Pentagon Action, [see box 7 and new accession at end of collection] (Box 3)
  - World Fellowship, Inc., 1952, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - World Gathering of Women for Disarmament, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - World Movement for World Federal Government, 1947, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - World Union of Women for International Concord, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Miscellaneous, 1937-39, 1967-86, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Another Mother for Peace
    - Brochures, cards, pamphlets, reprints and miscellaneous, 1962-76, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Newsletters, Aug 1967-85 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bess Myerson: speech and film, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War
    - Conference reports, 1925-33, [see also books on shelf] (Box 5)
    - Conference programs, 1937-40 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Organization, projects, seminars, etc., 1934-59, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Round table discussions, study outlines, 1938, 1940, 1941(?) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Women Strike for Peace
    - Memo, 1964-73, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Mailings, flyers, calendars, minutes, etc. 1962-75, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Newsletter, 1963-75 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Song, recording, 1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Women's Committee to Oppose Conscription
    - Statement of purpose, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Letters to members, 1943-47, undated (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    - Minutes, 1943-46 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Pamphlets, 1943, 1951, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Speech by Mildred Scott Olmsted, 1944, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Women's Encampment for a Future of Peace and Justice (newsletter), 1983, undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Women's Pentagon Action, 1980, undated, [see also Oversize materials and new accessions at end of collection] (Box 7, Folder 8-9)
  - Women's International League for Peace and Freedom
    - General (Box 7)
      - Clippings, 1915-75, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Constitution: International, 1934, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - History, 1929(?), 1938, 1940(?), [see books on shelf] (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Anniversaries, 1950, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Fiftieth Anniversary, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - National Peace Conference, 1937(?) (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Photographs, 1935, 1965, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Eugenie S. Intemann (Box 8)
      - Clippings, 1938-55, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
        - General (A-Z), 1933-75, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
        - Arnett, Katharine, 1952-69 (Box 9, Folder 3)
        - Baer, Gertrude, 1940-69, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
        - Balch, Emily Greene, 1942-46, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
        - Blake, Katherine Devereaux, 1935-50, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
        - Detzer, Dorothy, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
        - Gage-Colby, Ruth, 1971-72 (Box 9, Folder 8)
        - Hull, Hannah Clothier, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 9)
        - Olmstead, Mildred Scott, 1937-83, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
        - Organizations (Box 9)
          - General, 1932-72, undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
          - WILPF, 1935-75, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
        - Miscellaneous personal, 1933-70, 1971(?), 1973, undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Copies of letters from Intemann, 1934-76, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Financial, 1932-74, undated (Box 9, Folder 15)
      - Notes, 1940-67, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
      - Notes (United Nations), 1966-70, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
      - Photographs, 1918-65, undated, [see also Flat File] (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Other organizations, 1940-67 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - International (Box 9)
      - International Conference for Permanent Peace: General and clippings, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
      - International Conference of Women on a New Peace, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Conference: Chemical Warfare, 1929 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Conference: Problem of Statelessness, 1930 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - International Congress of Women (Box 10)
        - General, 1915 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        - Third International Congress, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        - Fourth International Congress, 1924 (Box 10, Folder 8-9)
        - Fifth International Congress, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 10)
        - Sixth International Congress, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 11)
        - Ninth International Congress, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 12)
        - Tenth International Congress, 1946 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, 1937-70, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - International Headquarters Advisory Council, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 15)
      - Executive Committee, 1927-71, undated (Box 10, Folder 16)
      - British Section, 1922-35, undated (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - French Section, 1923-30, undated (Box 10, Folder 18)
      - Netherlands Section, 1938-39 (Box 10, Folder 19)
      - Swedish Section, 1924-46 (Box 10, Folder 20)
      - Inter-American Congress of Women, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 21)
      - Congresses (Box 10)
        - 12th International Congress, 1953 (Box 11, Folder 1)
        - 13th International Congress, 1956 (Box 11)
        - 14th International Congress, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 2)
        - 15th International Congress, 1962 (Box 11, Folder 3)
        - 50th Anniversary Congress, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 4)
        - 17th International Congress, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 5)
        - 18th International Congress, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
        - 19th International Congress, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Circular letters, 1938-72 (Box 12, Folder 1-6)
      - International News, 1947-51 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - United States Section (Box 12)
      - History and constitution, 1938, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Organization, 1954-56, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - National Board, 1932-73, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - National President, 1942-68, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Executive Director, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Executive Secretary, 1940-45, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Administrative Secretary, 1948-66 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Organization Secretary, 1941, 1945, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Handbooks, 1938-65, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Manuals, 1937-68, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Branch letters, 1929-1970 (Box 14, Folder 1-4)
      - Organization letters, 1938-49 (Box 14, Folder 5-6)
      - Washington Newsletter, 1940-69 (Box 14, Folder 7-9)
      - Annual meeting reports, 1935-59 (Box 15, Folder 1-15)
      - Annual meeting reports, 1960-69 (Box 16, Folder 1-8)
      - Annual meeting notices, 1970-71 (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - Biennial meetings, 1973, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Committees
        - Art for World Friendship, 1954-66, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
        - Committee on Branches, 1964-69, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
        - Childhood Education, 1957-66, undated (Box 17, Folder 3)
        - Civil Liberties, 1943-66 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        - Civil Rights, 1958-66 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        - Conscientious Objection, 1943-48, undated (Box 17, Folder 6)
        - National Executive Committee, 1938-66, undated (Box 17, Folder 7)
        - Finance and Membership Committee, 1939-73, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
        - Human Rights, 1955-65 (Box 17, Folder 9)
        - National Labor Committee, 1944, undated (Box 17, Folder 10)
        - Labor Contracts Committee, 1965-66 (Box 17, Folder 11)
        - Latin American Affairs, 1955, 1966 (Box 17, Folder 12)
        - Legislative Committee, 1946-70, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
        - Literature 1938-69, undated (Box 17, Folder 14)
        - Membership, 1939-69, undated (Box 17, Folder 15)
        - Nominating, 1943-66, undated (Box 17, Folder 16)
        - Policy, 1947-67, undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
        - Program/Action, 1933-73, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
        - Public Relations, 1950-59, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
        - Publicity, 1956-67, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
        - Race Relations, 1946 (Box 18, Folder 5)
        - National Refugee, 1940-44, undated (Box 18, Folder 6)
        - Religious Contacts, 1942-68, undated (Box 18, Folder 7)
        - Resolutions, 1957, 1959 (Box 18, Folder 8)
        - Scientific Contacts, 1964-66 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        - UN, 1948-70, undated (Box 18, Folder 10)
        - Work for International, 1947(?), 1955-66 (Box 18, Folder 11)
        - World Development and World Disarmament, 1953-63 (Box 18, Folder 12)
        - World Government and Disarmament, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 13)
        - Miscellaneous, 1941-64, undated (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - Correspondence, 1930-74, undated (Box 19, Folder 1-6)
      - Publications and printed materials, [see also Flat File] (Box 19)
        - Lists (Box 20, Folder 1)
        - 1920-1969 (Box 20, Folder 2-6)
        - 1970+ (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - State and regional branches and conferences (Box 20)
        - California, 1938-65 (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - Colorado, 1939(?), 1969 (Box 21, Folder 2)
        - Illinois, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 3)
        - Massachusetts, 1944-64, [see also box 22A] (Box 21, Folder 4)
        - Michigan, 1939-68 (Box 21, Folder 5)
        - Minnesota, 1938, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
        - New Jersey, 1938-64 (Box 21, Folder 7)
        - New York, 1930-67, undated (Box 21, Folder 8-10)
        - New York branches, 1937-64, undated, [see also box 22] (Box 21, Folder 11)
        - Pennsylvania, 1940-54, undated (Box 21, Folder 12)
        - Washington, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 13)
        - New York Regional Conference, 1967 (Box 21, Folder 14)
        - Northeast Regional Conference, 1970-74, undated (Box 21, Folder 15)
        - Southern Regional Conference, 1966 (Box 21, Folder 16)
        - Manhattan branch
          - General, 1930-49 (Box 22, Folder 1)
          - Minute book for the board, 1936-40 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        - Metropolitan branch
          - General, 1950-75, undated (Box 22, Folder 3-7)
          - Metropolitan Branch News Bulletin, 1957-71 (Box 22a, Folder 1)
        - Northampton (Mass.) branch, 1959-70, undated (Box 22a, Folder 2-3)
    - Jane Addams
      - General, 1944-69, undated (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Jane Addams Centennial, 1955-61, undated (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Jane Addams Children's Book Award, 1964-67 (Box 23, Folder 3)
      - Jane Addams International Peace Fund, 1942-54 (Box 23, Folder 4)
      - Jane Addams Peace Association, 1964-75 (Box 23, Folder 5)
      - Jane Addams Peace Center, 1940, undated (Box 23, Folder 6)
      - Jane Addams Peace School, 1939-40 (Box 23, Folder 7)
      - Miscellaneous, 1930-75, undated (Box 24, Folder 1-6)
  - Women's Pentagon Action (Box 24)
    [Restricted until 2022: may not identify WPA participants without their permission- researchers must sign Access Agreement Form before viewing these records]
    - Photographs and posters (oversize box), [see also Flat File] (Box 25)
    - First Action, November 16th and I7th, 1980: Minutes, agendas, publicity, reports, and photocopies of photographs (Box 26)
    - Second Action, November 16th and 17th, 1981: Proposals, minutes, publicity, reports, and songs (Box 26)
    - Unity statements, flyers and other printed material, and mailing and contact lists (Box 26)
    - Prison and civil disobedience: Lists, prison records, printed material, correspondence, statements, poems, and notes (Box 26)
    - New York City Women's Pentagon Action: Flyers, mailings, articles, correspondence, and materials related to their involvement with Seneca Women's Peace Encampment (Box 26)
    - "Not in our Name" action, New York City, November 18th and 19th, 1984: Minutes, reports, publicity, and responses to mailing (Box 26)
    - Print media coverage of the first and second actions (Box 26)
    - "Women Against the Pentagon," Nov 16-17, 1980: a documentary by Kate Donnelly (20 minute videotape) (Box 26)
    - Buttons (Box 26)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - WILPF (Map-case Flat File)
    - Posters: "The Bridge of Peace" and "Without disarmament... who will have grandchildren?"undated (Map-case Flat File)
    - Canvas banner, undated (Map-case Flat File)
    - Intemann, Eugenie: photograph of New York Normal School graduating class and photograph of Association Camp, 1909, 1963 (Map-case Flat File)
  - Women's Pentagon Action: posters, 1981, undated, [see also box 25] (Map-case Flat File)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Balch, Emily Greene. Approaches to the Great Settlement, 1918
  - Brittain, Vera. The Rebel Passion, 1964
  - Bussey, Gertrude and Margaret Tims. Women's International League for Peace and Freedom, 1915-1965; a Record of Fifty Years' Work, 1965
  - Degen, Marie Louise. The History of the Woman's Peace Party, 1974 (reprint of 1939 ed.)
  - Hadden, Maude Miner. Quest for Peace: Personal and Political, 1968
  - Report of the Conference on Cause and Cure of War, Washington, D.C., Jan 18-24, 1925 (2 vols.)